Geraldine Farrar Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Geraldine Farrar Collection1895-1943 (bulk 1898-1939)
ML31.F4
Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967
circa 25,000 items 58 boxes 17 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Geraldine Farrar was an American opera singer and film actress. The collection consists of Farrar's personal papers relating to her life and career, including correspondence, scrapbooks and clippings, photographs and music materials containing sketches, autograph manuscripts, and printed music composed or edited by Farrar. In addition, the collection contains biographical materials, Farrar's writings, contracts, radio scripts, concert programs, awards and other miscellaneous items.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Belasco, David, 1853-1931--Correspondence.; Businger, Ruth A., 1893-1965--Correspondence.; Carreño, Teresa, 1853-1917--Correspondence.; Caruso, Enrico, 1873-1921--Correspondence.; Cecilie, Crown Princess of the German Empire and of Prussia, 1886-1954--Correspondence.; Charpentier, Gustave, 1860-1956--Correspondence.; DeMille, Cecil B. (Cecil Blount), 1881-1959--Correspondence.; Dukas, Paul, 1865-1935--Correspondence.; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967--Archives.; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967--Correspondence.; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967--Manuscripts.; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967--Photographs.; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967.; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967.; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967. Such sweet compulsion.; Finck, Henry Theophilus, 1854-1926--Correspondence.; Hadley, Henry Kimball, 1871-1937--Correspondence.; Hahn, Reynaldo, 1875-1947--Correspondence.; Humperdinck, Engelbert, 1854-1921--Correspondence.; Humphries, Daisy--Correspondence.; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971--Correspondence.; Kreisler, Fritz, 1875-1962--Correspondence.; Lehmann, Lilli, 1848-1929--Correspondence.; Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912--Correspondence.; Pons, Lily, 1898-1976--Correspondence.; Puccini, Giacomo, 1858-1924--Correspondence.; Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1873-1943--Correspondence.; Toscanini, Arturo, 1867-1957--Correspondence.; William, Crown Prince of Germany, 1882-1951--Correspondence.
Organizations
Goldwyn Pictures Corporation.; Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects
Motion picture actors and actresses--United States.; Music--Manuscripts.; Opera.; Sopranos (Singers)--United States.; Women singers--United States.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Clippings (Information artifacts); Contracts.; Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Scrapbooks.; Scripts (Documents).
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Geraldine Farrar; 1954-1964.
Custodial History
In 1954, the Library of Congress purchased fifteen letters written by Geraldine Farrar (1882-1967) to her long-time friend Mrs. Daisy Humphries. Later in 1954, Farrar donated her personal papers to the Library. Together, these two acquisitions, containing numerous scrapbooks, correspondence, and photographs, formed the basis for the Geraldine Farrar Collection, which documents the career of one of America's most celebrated sopranos. Subsequent gifts by Farrar in 1958, 1959, and 1964 added additional materials to the collection. Other materials were added to the collection from time to time, including letters from Farrar to Ruth A. Businger, donated by Businger in 1967, and a photo of Farrar dating from 1967 and donated by Edwin A. McArthur in 1982. Additionally, several letters from Farrar to Florence Mosher were purchased in 1970.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Farrar's original gift contained a set of fifty-five phonograph records. These were transferred to the Library of Congress, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division.
Access and Restrictions
The Geraldine Farrar Collection is open to research. The status of the literary rights in any of the unpublished writings or compositions contained in this collection is unclear; certain materials may be restricted with respect to use and/or copying.
Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1882, Feb. 28 Born, Melrose, Massachusetts to Sidney "Sid" Farrar, former player with the Philadelphia Athletics, and Henrietta Barnes Farrar
1894-1898 Studied voice with Mrs. J.H. Long in Boston and Emma Thursby in Manhattan; performed for Lillian Nordica and Nellie Melba
1899-1900 Farrar family moved to Paris and then Berlin to further Geraldine's career
1901 Began life-long association with Kaiser Wilhelm II and family
1901, Oct. 15 Berlin Hofoper debut as Marguerite in Gounod's Faust
1903 Began vocal training with Lilli Lehmann
1903 May Studied the role of Manon with composer Jules Massenet in Paris
1903, Dec. 1 Premiere of Manon in Berlin
1903-1906 Performed with Monte Carlo Opera
1905, Mar. 8 Mascagni's Amica, world premiere
1906, Feb. 24 Saint-Saëns' L'Ancêtre, world premiere
1906 Summer Metropolitan Opera contract
1906 Oct. Declined Strauss' request to premiere Salomé at the Berlin Royal Opera
1906, Nov. 26 Metropolitan Opera debut in Gounod's Romeo et Juliet
1907, Feb. 11 Metropolitan Opera premiere of Puccini's Madama Butterfly
1910, Dec. 28 Humperdinck's Königskinder, world premiere
1914, Jan. 3 Metropolitan Opera, first American production of Wolf-Ferrari's Le Donne Curiose
1914, Nov. 19 Metropolitan Opera, plays the first of fifty-seven sold-out performances of Carmen
1914 Metropolitan Opera, Gustave Charpentier's Julien, premiere
1915-1919 Cecil B. DeMille films, including Carmen, Maria Rosa, Temptation, The Woman God Forgot, and Joan the Woman
1916, Feb. 8 Married actor and director Lou Tellegen in New York
1918 Metropolitan Opera, Puccini's Suor Angelica, world premiere
1922 Apr. Made final performance at the Metropolitan Opera as the title character in Leoncavallo's Zazá, her last appearance on the opera stage
1922-1931 Toured as concert singer, concentrating on Lieder
1923 Divorces Lou Tellegen
1931 Retired from singing career
1934-1935 Hosted Metropolitan Opera radio broadcasts
1935-1967 Public service activities including work with the Red Cross, the American Women's Volunteer Service Transport, the Office of Price Administration, and the Republican Party
1938 Published autobiography Such Sweet Compulsion
1967, Mar. 11 Died, Ridgefield, Connecticut
Scope and Content
Biographical Materials series in the collection include drafts in several versions for Farrar's autobiography Such Sweet Compulsion. Additionally, the Writings series contains a lecture titled "Vocal Treatise with record illustrations" as well as the typescript for a book of vocal exercises. These vocal treatises are complemented by three books of Farrar's vocal exercises dating from 1923 to 1925. Also of note are Farrar's lectures, "The Effects of War on Music," and "Music in a War-torn World," both written during World War II. The writings also include numerous versions of a lecture on the history of music titled "Music through the ages." The majority of the lectures date from the years following Farrar's retirement from her opera career in 1922.
The Music series contains both printed and manuscript items. The compositions by Farrar are exclusively for voice with piano accompaniment; the majority date from the late 1930's. During her tenure at the Metropolitan Opera, Farrar attracted large numbers of young admirers, who were known as the "Gerryflappers." Many of the original compositions which Farrar wrote in her retirement, such as "The Little Christmas Donkey" and "The Easter Robin," were written for the children of these admirers. Music arranged or translated by Farrar, including several vocal arrangements of works by Rachmaninoff and Kreisler, is also included.
Within the Correspondence series are letters, picture postcards, telegrams, and various personal notes both to and from Geraldine Farrar. The materials reflect both her private and public life. Among the more insightful and interesting materials is Farrar's life-long correspondence with Germany's Crown Prince Wilhem (1882-1951) and Crown Princess Cecelie. At Farrar's request, these letters, dating as early as 1901, remained sealed until 1979, along with other documents sent to Farrar by the German royal family. There is also a considerable amount of correspondence from the American producer David Belasco (1853-1931), Farrar's voice coach Lilli Lehmann (1848-1929), and close friends Daisy Humphries and Ruth A. Businger (1893-1965). Among the notable correspondents are Teresa Carreño, Enrico Caruso, Gustave Charpentier, Cecil B. DeMille, Paul Dukas, Henry T. Finck, Henry Hadley, Reynaldo Hahn, Engelbert Humperdinck, Rockwell Kent, Fritz Kreisler, Jules Massenet, Lily Pons, Giacomo Puccini, Sergei Rachmaninof and Arturo Toscanini.
Farrar's contracts with the Metropolitan Opera from 1908 to 1918 comprise the bulk of the Contracts series. There are also a considerable amount of film contracts with the Goldwyn Pictures Corporation, dating from 1915 to 1919. Farrar's contract with the Berlin Royal Opera dates from 1904 while a contract dated 1940 regarding royalties from her autobiography with Greystone Press, is the most recent. Illustrative of Farrar's popularity as both a prima donna and an actress is her contract with Benjamin Claggett in 1917 regarding the production and distribution of "Geraldine Farrar Candy." Included among the contracts and business-related materials are Along with contracts are other business related materials, such as concert tour itineraries and receipts.
The Scripts series contains scripts for radio programs and pageants in both manuscript and typescript forms. These reflect Farrar's career as a musical commentator for various radio programs and as a volunteer in civic organizations after her retirement from opera singing. The majority of the scripts are from the years 1934 and 1935 including scripts from Farrar's guest appearances in the Metropolitan Opera broadcasts, the script from the General Electric Show on February 14, 1932 is the earliest.
The programs in the Programs series date from Farrar's first recitals in Melrose, Massachusetts, during her teenage years, to her final appearances as a concert singer in 1931. A large number of the programs are from the 1914-22 Metropolitan Opera seasons. Additionally, there are numerous programs from Farrar's concert recitals, dating from 1922 to 1934.
The overwhelming majority of materials in the collection is found in 43 scrapbooks that cover Farrar's entire life and career. A large number of the scrapbooks, particularly the oversize scrapbooks (boxes 28, 44, 45, and 46), are in poor condition, with many loose and brittle pages. Several scrapbooks (those dating from before 1898-1898, 1914-1919, and 1919-1921) contain numerous photographs. The scrapbook from 1914-19 contains several pages of photos of Farrar taken during World War I to publicize the War Bonds Drive and the Victrola Records Campaign. All of the scrapbooks in the collection should be handled with extreme care.
The Civic Materials series contains an assortment of governmental papers, forms, and notes, such as an auto log-book and lists of telephone numbers. These materials represent Farrar's participation in the Red Cross and various governmental organizations during World War II. One of the more interesting items is Farrar's sketchbook containing pencil drawings of airplanes, done while she was a ground observer in the American Women's Voluntary Service of the Army Air Force in 1943.
The Photographs and Iconography series documents Farrar's entire life and career. In addition to the many individual photographs, there are also two boxes of photographs (box 49, folders 5-8 and box 50) that were originally bound in two scrapbooks containing only photographs. Three books of film stills from Farrar's films Maria Rosa, Carmen, and The Temptation are also in the collection. A large painting of Farrar by Friedrich August von Kaulbach is part of the collection and is currently located in the administrative offices of the Music Division.
The items in the Awards and Certificates series date from the last forty years of Farrar's life and relate to her many civic and artistic activities. They include her ASCAP and Society of American Arts and Letters membership certificates. Items in the Miscellany series include several fans used by Farrar in Madama Butterfly, a framed portion of the curtain from the old Metropolitan Opera house given to her in 1940, as well as several medals and awards for her public service activities.
Antonio de Guzman, Junior Fellow 1995
Peter Schmerz, Junior Fellow 1995
Robert Saladini, Music Specialist
Organization of the Geraldine Farrar Collection
The Geraldine Farrar Collection is organized in thirteen series:
Biographical Materials
Writings by Geraldine Farrar
Music
Correspondence
Contracts, 1908-1919
Scripts
Programs, 1895-1934
Awards and Certificates
Clippings
Scrapbooks, 1898-1941
Civic Materials
Photographs and Iconography
Miscellany
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006560270
Container List
- Biographical Materials (Box 1-3)
  Biographical materials in the collection include drafts in several versions for Farrar's autobiography Such Sweet Compulsion.
  Arrangement is by subseries and then by format.
  - Autobiographical
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, drafts (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, working copy (one of three) (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, working copy (two of three) (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, working copy (three of three) (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, uncorrected copy (one of three) (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, uncorrected copy (two of three) (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, uncorrected copy (three of three) (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, final manuscript (one of three) (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, final manuscript (two of three) (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, final manuscript (three of three) (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion, plates (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Farrar exhibit, drafts (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Prima Donna Holiday, typescript (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Biographical
    - Articles and interviews (alphabetical by title) (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Wagenknecht, Edward. Geraldine Farrar: An Authorized Record of Her Career. Seattle: University Book Store, 1929. (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Unknown author. Geraldine Farrar. Bound typescript in German. (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Farrar family genealogy (Box-folder 3/1)
- Writings by Geraldine Farrar (Box 3-4)
  Writings by Farrar including vocal treatises, lectures and speeches and general writings.
  Arrangement is by subseries, then alphabetical by title.
  - Vocal Treatises
    - Vocal treatise, drafts (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Vocal treatise (one of two) (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Vocal treatise (two of two) (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Lectures and Speeches
    - Lectures (one of two) (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Lectures (two of two) (Box-folder 3/6)
    - "Effects of War on Music" (Box-folder 3/7)
    - "A Survey of Music History with records," several versions (one of four) (Box-folder 3/8)
    - "A Survey of Music History with records" (two of four) (Box-folder 4/1)
    - "A Survey of Music History with records" (three of four) (Box-folder 4/2)
    - "A Survey of Music History with records" (four of four) (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Political speeches (Box-folder 4/4)
  - General Writings
    - Articles, drafts (alphabetical by title) (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Miscellaneous writings (unpublished articles and other writings) (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Translations
    - Translations (song lyrics and articles about Farrar) (Box-folder 4/7)
- Music (Box 5-7)
  The music in the collection is in both printed and manuscript form. The compositions by Farrar are exclusively for voice with piano accompaniment; the majority date from the late 1930's.
  Arrangement is by subseries, then alphabetical by composer and title.
  - Music composed by Geraldine Farrar
    - Chil Chil Blue and Co Che Bang., Lyric sheets and sketches (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Child's Christmas Carol., Sketches (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Concert Aria (Liebesfreud)., Sketches (Box-folder 5/3)
    - The Easter Robin., Sketches (Box-folder 5/4)
    - The Easter Robin. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1938. (Box-folder 5/5)
    - The Fan., Lyric sheet and sketches (Box-folder 5/6)
    - The Four Winds--For Children's Pageant., Holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Frülingsglaube., Sketches (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Hymn., Sketches (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Hymn for Maccabuc Memorial Church., Sketches (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Invitation (Souvenir For Lily)., Sketches, holograph piano-vocal score; Includes: Printed draft with corrections (Box-folder 5/11)
    - The Infant Jesus Lullaby., Lyrics and sketches (Box-folder 5/12)
    - The Legend of the Dogwood Tree., Lyric sheets and sketches (Box-folder 5/13)
    - The Little Christmas Donkey., Lyric sheets and holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/14)
    - The Little Christmas Donkey. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1938. (Box-folder 5/15)
    - Little Valse For Nancy., Sketches (Box-folder 5/16)
    - Little Waltz For Nancy. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1938. (Box-folder 5/17)
    - Message., Sketch (Box-folder 5/18)
    - The Miniature., Sketches and holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/19)
    - The Miniature. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1938. (Box-folder 5/20)
    - Minnelied (Hölty) [May Carol]., Holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/21)
    - Morning., Holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/22)
    - My Heart Sings., Holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/23)
    - My Neighbor's Curtain., Sketches (Box-folder 5/24)
    - Nostalgia., Sketches (Box-folder 5/25)
    - Oiseaux., Sketches (Box-folder 5/26)
    - Spring Wooing., Sketches (Box-folder 5/27)
    - Spring Wooing. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1938. (Box-folder 5/28)
    - Slumber Song., Sketches and holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/29)
    - Slumber Song. New York: Charles Foley, 1939. (Box-folder 5/30)
    - The Song of The Quail., Holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/31)
    - Spring Song., Lyric sheets (Box-folder 5/32)
    - The Swallows., Lyric sheet and sketches (Box-folder 5/33)
    - Valse Caressante., Sketches and holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/34)
    - Whisper You Care., Holograph piano-vocal score (Box-folder 5/35)
    - Whisper You Care. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1938. (Box-folder 5/36)
    - Xmas Greeting., Sketches and printed Christmas card version (Box-folder 5/37)
    - Catalog--Compositions and Arrangements by Geraldine Ferrar (Box-folder 5/38)
    - Miscellaneous sketches, title unknown (Box-folder 5/39)
    - Vocal Exercises (Box-folder 5/40)
  - Music edited and/or arranged by Geraldine Farrar
    - Bach, J.S.
      - Supplication (Air on the G String)., Sketches (Box-folder 6/1)
      - Supplication (Air on the G String). New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1937. (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Beethoven, Ludwig van
      - Evening., Sketches (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Gilmour, Howard
      - Mandarin Princess., Sketches; Lyrics by Farrar (Box-folder 6/4)
      - Mandarin Princess. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1938. (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Kreisler, Fritz
      - Liebesfreud (Love's Delight)., Farrar's sketches and printed; For 2 pianos by Kreisler (Box-folder 6/6)
      - Song of May: A Viennese Love Song. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1935., Note: Based on the composer's "Liebesfreud"; Poem and Vocal Setting by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/7)
      - Love Comes and Goes: A Viennese Love Song. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1934., Note: Based on the composer's "Liebeslied"; Poem and Vocal Setting by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/8)
      - The Old Refrain (Viennese Popular Song)., Farrar's lyric sheets and printed copy of Kreisler original (Box-folder 6/9)
      - Dear Homeland: Viennese Popular Song. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1915., Note: Based on the composer's "The Old Refrain"; Poem and Vocal Setting By Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/10)
      - Schön Rosmarin (Fair Rosmarin)., Farrar's lyric sheets, sketches, and printed copy of Kreisler original (Box-folder 6/11)
      - Fair Rosmarin: A Viennese Love Song. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1935., Note: Based on the composer's "Schön Rosmarin"; Poem and Vocal Setting by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/12)
      - Shepherd's Madrigal., Farrar's sketches and printed copy of Kreisler original (Box-folder 6/13)
      - Shepherd's Madrigal: Old German. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1937. (Box-folder 6/14)
      - The Whole World Knows: A Viennese Love Song. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1934., Note: Based on the composer's "Caprice Viennois"; Poem and Vocal Setting by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/15)
    - Moussorgsky, Modest
      - Tears: Song for Voice and Piano. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1935., Poem and Vocal Setting by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/16)
    - Rachmaninoff, Sergei
      - Mélodie, Op. 3, no. 3., Printed version of Rachmaninoff original and sketches for Farrar's version, titled "Reverie" (Box-folder 6/17)
    - Schumann, Robert
      - Slumber Song., Sketches (Box-folder 6/18)
    - Tchaikovsky, Pyotr Il'yich
      - Challenge. New York: Charles Foley, 1940., Words and Vocal Arrangement by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/19)
      - Dialogue., Sketches (Box-folder 6/20)
      - Romeo and Juliet., Sketches; Note: Aria excerpt (Box-folder 6/21)
      - Juliet's Farewell. New York: Charles Foley, 1940., Lyrics and Vocal Arrangement by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/22)
  - Vocal works translated by Geraldine Farrar
    - Grechaninov, Alexandr Tikhonovich
      - The Wounded Birch, Op. 1, No.2., Printed edition with pencil translation.; Lyrics by A. Tolstoi (Box-folder 6/23)
    - Kreisler, Fritz
      - Liebeslied: Duett aus dem Singspiel "Sissy"., Printed edition with pencil translation; Note: Translated as "Love Comes and Goes" (Box-folder 6/24)
    - Lehar, Franz
      - Oh Wie Schön., Music and lyric sheets in Farrar's hand (Box-folder 6/25)
    - Loewe, Carl
      - Die Oasis. Der "Bilder des Orients", Op. 10, No. 4., Printed edition with pencil translation. (Box-folder 6/26)
    - Rachmaninoff, Sergei
      - The Alder Tree (Before my window). New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1922., Russian lyrics by G. Galina; English version by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/27)
      - The Fountain, Op. 26, No. 11. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1922., Words by Th. Tjuttschew; English version by Geraldine Farrar; Also printed edition of song with pencil translation. (Box-folder 6/28)
      - Here Beauty Dwells. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1922., Russian lyrics by G. Galina; English version by Geraldine Farrar; Publisher's proofs and copy of final printed version. (Box-folder 6/29)
      - The Mirage. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1922., Russian lyrics by K. Balmont (after Shelley); English version by Geraldine Farrar (Box-folder 6/30)
    - Schumann, Robert
      - Sängerstrost (Singer's Consolation), Op. 127, no. 1., Manuscript, music and translation in Farrar's hand. (Box-folder 6/31)
    - Unknown
      - Betracht dies Herz., Sketches (Box-folder 6/32)
      - Kommet her ihr armen Sünder., Sketches (Box-folder 6/33)
  - Music By Other Composers
    - Chamade
      - The Silver Ring. (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Farrar, Geraldine, arranger